All right friends, so in the last video we had a look at a detailed look rather at methods
and how they're useful, why do we use them every day in a programming lives and what purpose
do they serve and we then have a look at when would we pass in no parameters when
would we have declared parameters 0 to n and when would we declare a return type and would
we have a method return a value back as well and then you saw I created different versions
of the same addition of two programs although they all meant the same to the end user but
in programming terms the last version was the best version yet and the exercise you would have created
one more version which would rather be the best version yet right and that just goes on
to tell you different versions of the same program does the same thing but some are efficient
others are not and again that tells you programming is always requirement driven and based on
your preference as a developer based on your style of coding what is that you would bring to the
table and we should always strive as I've been repeatedly telling you it has become a cliche now
that is we should always aim for writing better readable quality code because in 2026
programming is no longer a rocket science right but what matters is how how better code you would
write how what is the level of the quality of your code and is it efficient is it succinct less
verbose those are the factors that would determine you being a good or a bad developer not just
a Java developer but a programmer a developer in general so with that we take this discussion forward
and get back to now polymorphism and you would remember me talking about polymorphism one face
many forms we are taken that real well analogy as well time to put that into practice and this is
the first way we implement polymorphism in Java and that's coming on for you in this video let's
just go on and create a new class quickly again so I'll just say a new class let's just call it
method overloading team
right and before we move on I just hope that you're not just just watching the scores although
that is good that's good for a start but what would drive you ahead is if you code with me
if you code alongside with me if you put in your efforts as well it's a two-way traffic that
would hold you in great state to to to move ahead in a really nice and and cool manner right
so getting back and I'll just have the main method as always and now let's say we have a class
again I'll just call it class calculate all right and what does it say sorry that's the syntax
error it says class calculate is never used we would use that thank you Mr. compiler for warning
us on that but don't worry we're going to use that so I'll just say I have a requirement again I want
to I have a requirement from the client that is I want to have a method which takes two arguments
and returns their multiplication for example so I'll just say wide multiply
right and should take two arguments I'll say int first
int second and you'll say return first multiplied second and obviously the return time now has
to be of type int because that's what we are returning right so this method when called would need
to be passed to our humans and return back the multiplication of two numbers obviously I'm not
calling it yet let's just go on and do that I'll say calculate let's say calculate is a reference
variable new calculate and I'll say calculate dot multiply and let's pass in the two numbers
which I'll take from user at runtime so I'll again say scanner let's call it scan new scanner
and I'll say system dot n and again ask the user to enter two numbers the same drill obviously
and just to make this code sucks and rather than getting the numbers right here and putting them
into two variables I'll just pass them directly this again goes on to tell you how we can write
less verb or score I'll just say scan dot next int and separated by comma scan dot next int
so the numbers are taken right within arguments to a method right and then they are passed as
arguments to the parameters we do the multiplication and this would be printed in a sound I'll say
let's put in a multiplication I'll say system dot or print L and this is multiply this is fine
and this just makes it complete and then I'll say that is the multiplication of two numbers is
right you've just printed out so let's just go on and run this let's stop this run this again
and bring it up a bit it says enter two numbers I'll say 12 I'll say 8 it says 96 works absolutely
fine but after some time the requirement changes they say that now there should be a method which
takes two arguments and returns their result but now there should be an option based on the user's
choice at runtime it should take three numbers and multiply their their result as well just print it
out but the two number thing should also be there you don't have to get rid of that so what I'll do
is I'll create one more method I'll say int multiply and this time I'll pass in in first
in second and in third and you you're guessing you're right where is this going I'll say return
first multiply second multiply third and please return the result right and I'll obviously need to
call it multiply three because obviously it multiplies three numbers right instead of two
all right so this is a method which multiplies two numbers and returns the result this is a method
which multiplies three numbers takes three arguments and returns their result their multiplication
right and but this is what's obviously when I call multiply three then at that time
that is the method that need would be called right here I'm just calling calculate multiply
so two number one is called but if you want that I'll just say control D again the shortcut
that is hit comment and this time I'll say enter three numbers right and I'll say result is
and then you will take one more number from the ramp time scan dot next int
all right takes three numbers now and calls multiply three and the arrow goes over here right
obviously in a real goal program you will just take it forward and create a menu driven program you
will say press and one if you want to multiply two numbers press two if you want to multiply
three numbers right but for now we're just calling either of them you get the idea right I'll just
hit run and this time it says enter three numbers now I'll say 34 I'll say two I'll say four
let's say two 72 perfectly fine after some time they say that now there should be these two
but there should be one more method which takes four arguments and returns the multiplication
of four numbers so I'll just copy base this as a programmer and I'll say multiply two numbers
okay and then I'll say int first in second in third and I'll say int fourth
and return the result of the multiplied four numbers all right that works fine as well so multiply
multiply three multiply four based on the method that I'm calling that would be called right
but after some time as a programmer I realize that this is redundant coding this is almost
writing repetitive code see you're just multiplying two numbers or three or four right in these three
methods you're multiplying numbers right but you would have to remember three different names
so that's when I say when your job is to essentially do the same thing with different methods
I'll repeat it again when your job is when your task is to do the same thing essentially the same
thing with different methods we do not have to name them differently right because you're
essentially multiplying why should I call them ugly like multiply three and multiply four right
so that is when polymorphism comes in remember one face many forms and the first way to implement
polymorphism in Java is method overloading right and what is that concept that says inside
a class now we can have more than one methods with the same name and that is called method
overloading a method is said to be overloading another method right so again inside one class
we can have multiple methods with the same name but and this is a bit but here but the rule is
because how would now the compiler if I just call this see first of all I can call them multiply
multiply and multiply three methods with the same name the first time you're seeing right
it isn't a conflict it's not an error why because polymorphism method overloading this method
is overloading this one this is overloading the other two right and we're just calling them the
same because they're just multiplying numbers why should we call them differently so it's a programming
convenience after disposal right so they say for overloading to work in a class you can have
different methods with the same name but the parameters have to be different because otherwise
how do the compiler resolve calls to these methods because they're all called the same if we
just call multiply there's no multiply three now so if you pass three or two or four parameters
how would it resolve it by the parameters by the arguments you pass in because the name is the same
right otherwise it would have been a conflict it would have been an ambiguity right and to resolve that
they say the rule is in a class you can have multiple methods with the same name but the parameters
have to be different and how do they be different is either their type or their number or their
sequence and here I'm sticking to the number of parameters being different that's why this is allowed
see if they were the same we should get an error it says you hover on this multiply intent
is already defined in org dot one dot calculate show multiply duplicates right so they're resolved
by the number or the type or the sequence of parameters you define right and that's why I would say
in third the error goes away essentially reads this as a different method a new method
but the name is the same right you just have to name them the same that is method overloading see
one face multiplies the face to the entire world but many forms that is polymorphism right
and again we just specify two parameters here three and here four depending on the arguments you
pass in if you pass in three the three parameter one would be called if you pass in the four
one the four one would be called if you pass in two arguments this first one would be called
so programming convenience that is method overloading the first way to implement polymorphism in
[BLANK_AUDIO]